## DR NATALIE COOPER

EMAIL: NCOOPER@TCD.IE TWITTER: @NHCOOPER123
WEBPAGE: WWW.TCD.IE/ZOOLOGY/RESEARCH/NCOOPER/NATALIECOOPER.PHP
GOOGLE SCHOLAR PROFILE: HTTP://GOO.GL/EHLTGG FIGSHARE: HTTP://GOO.GL/F2DPGH
ORCID: 10000-0003-4919-8655 RESEARCHERID: I-7976-2012

#### **RESEARCH INTERESTS**

My research sits at the interface between macroecology and macroevolution, and aims to understand broad-scale patterns of biodiversity. I use cutting-edge phylogenetic comparative methods, morphological data collected from museum specimens, phylogenies, ecological data, species geographic range maps, fossils and various larger databases, to investigate a variety of questions including the influence of competition on macroevolutionary patterns, rates and modes of evolution, and the evolutionary ecology of zoonotic diseases.

#### **ACADEMIC CAREER**

2012-present	Assistant Professor, School of Natural Sciences, Trinity College Dublin.
2010-2011	Postdoctoral Fellow, Human Evolutionary Biology, Harvard University.
2009-2010	Postdoctoral Associate, Ecology and Evolutionary Biology, Yale University.

#### **EDUCATION**

2005-2009	Ph.D, Phylogenetic approaches for studying competition in mammals					
	Imperial College London & Institute of Zoology.					
	Supervisor: Prof. Andy Purvis; Co-supervisor: Prof. Kate Jones					
2004-2005	M.Sc. (Distinction), Advanced Methods in Taxonomy and Biodiversity					
	Imperial College London & Natural History Museum.					
2001-2004	B.Sc. (1st class honours) Biological Sciences, University of Exeter.					

# **GRANTS AND AWARDS**

2012	Marie Curie Career Integration Grant (CIG) for project Evolutionary	€100,000
	Ecology and Fossil Primates.	
2009	Seessel Postdoctoral Fellowship for Innovative Research in Biology.	\$37,000

### INTERNATIONAL CONFERENCE PRESENTATIONS

2014	Evolution	The "Dark Side" of phylogenetic comparative methods (symposium).
2013	Evolution	Ecological correlates of extrinsic mortality in mammals and birds.
2012	Evolution	Host phylospecificity and parasite sharing in primates and humans.
2011	EEID	Methods for detecting phylogenetic host specificity in parasites (poster).
2010	<b>Evolution</b>	Phylogenetic niche conservatism in mammals.
2008	Evolution	A common pattern of overdispersion in mammalian assemblages.

## **INVITED SEMINAR TALKS**

- 2013 Ecology & Environment Seminar Series, University of Southampton.
- 2013 Ecology, Evolution & Environment Seminar Series, University of Sheffield.
- 2013 Biological Sciences Seminar Series, University of Liverpool.
- 2013 Evolutionary Morphology (EvMorph) Seminar Series, University of Chicago.
- 2011 Museum of Comparative Zoology Seminar Series, Harvard University.

#### PROFESSIONAL SERVICE

2014-present	Member of BES Publications Committee.
2013-present	Organiser of #MacroJC, a tri-continental online macroevolution journal club.
2013-present	Member of School of Natural Sciences INTEGER committee on Gender
_	Equality (and website maintainer).
2013-present	Evolutionary Biology & Ecology seminar series organiser.
2012-present	Organiser of NERD club, a weekly Ecology and Evolution research group
1	meeting for staff and PhD students across the School of Natural Sciences.
2013-present	Grant reviewer for UK Natural Environment Research Council (NERC).
2013-present	Grant reviewer for Canadian National Science Foundation (NSERC).
2012-present	Member of British Ecological Society (BES) including Macroecology Group.
2013-present	Member of Society of Systematic Biologists.

#### PUBLIC ENGAGEMENT AND OUTREACH

2014	Organiser of SoapBox Science Ireland - an outreach event featuring women				
	in science explaining their research in an interactive way.				
2013 & 2014	Organiser and tour guide for Discover Research Dublin at the TCD Zoology				
	Museum, as part of European Researcher's Night.				
2013-present	EcoEvo@TCD blog developer and contributor. The blog has had over 44,300				
_	views and over 220 posts.				
2012-present	Active Twitter user (@nhcooper123) with over 1200 followers and over 6000				
-	tweets.				

## **TEACHING EXPERIENCE**

# POSTGRADUATE STUDENT SUPERVISION

PhD	2012-2015	Thomas Guillerme	Evolutionary ecology and primates	TCD
MRes	2012-2014	Sive Finlay	Convergent evolution in tenrecs	TCD
MSc	2013	Marta Capolei	Host phylospecificity in parasites	TCD

## UNDERGRADUATE AND TAUGHT POSTGRADUATE

2012-present	Intro to Biodiversity, Evolution & the Environment	Year 1	TCD
2012-present	Comparative Physiology (Vertebrate Biomechanics)	Year 3	TCD
2013-present	Research Comprehension	Year 4	TCD
2012-present	Taxonomy & Systematics	MSc	TCD

# POSTGRADUATE, POSTDOCS AND STAFF

2013-present	Computer Skills (LaTeX, R, git etc.)					TCD
2010-2012	AnthroTree	Phylogenetic	Comparative	Methods	All	-
	workshop					

## **JOURNAL REVIEWING**

The American Naturalist, Animal Conservation, BMC Evolutionary Biology, Conservation Biology, Ecology and Evolution, Ecology Letters, Evolution, Global Ecology & Biogeography, International Journal of Primatology, Journal of Animal Ecology, Journal of Biogeography, Journal of Evolutionary Biology, Methods in Ecology & Evolution, Oecologia, Philosophical Transactions of the Royal Society: B, PLoS One, Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences USA, Proceedings of the Royal Society: B, Trends in Ecology & Evolution.